Come on, kids, out of the street. Come on, kids, get back there.
快点，小家伙，到那边去 快点，小家伙，回到那边
Hey, you. Get out of there!
嗨 就是你走开
Get out of the street!
到路边去
Clear the street!
到路边去 别挡着路
Get away from there!
走开
Get out of the way, old man. can't you hear?
小心别挡着路 没听到吗
can't you see you're in the way? Get out of here!
看不到你挡着路了吗 走开
- All right. - Out of the way!
好好好
Watch out, old-timer.
看着点老家伙
You got a good horse, but not good enough. I'll have that dollar.
―你的马不错 但还不够好 一美金归我了
I'm beginning to figure these races smell bad.
我开始觉得这些比赛挺无聊的
That thing never loses.
这家伙还从来没输过
- You had your chance. - Well, let's just say I'm a poor loser.
―你本来有机会赢的 ―好吧就算我是个没钱的失败者好了
So if you want this dollar...
想要这美元
...you just come right on over here and get it, sonny boy.
那你直接走到我这来自己拿，小男孩
Right this way, folks. Come one, come all.
这边，朋友们到这边来 大家都过来呀
Step right up and try your luck. Everybody welcome.
来试试你的运气 任何人都可以
See the Oregon Kid in person.
亲眼看看这个依勒冈小子
Right this way, folks. Come one, come all.
来这边，朋友们， 快来，大家都来
Step right up and outshoot the famous Oregon Kid.
站出来射一枪，赢了这个依勒冈小子
The last of the Western town-tamers.
最后的西部城市征服者
Fatten your wallets and be a hero to your family. Everybody welcome.
放开钱袋，成为家族的荣耀，任何人都可以来
Step up. Try your luck. All you gotta do is hit the plates, and you win the money.
站出来，试试你的运气，只要射中盘子，钱就归你拉
- Quit the sermon and turn her loose. - One dollar on the yellow.
别管什么布道了，先放开娘儿们 一美元射黄色那个
Shooting against you is like sneaking licorice from a baby girI.
跟你比射击就像从个小女婴手里偷根草
Care to try again?
要不要再试一次
Mister, could I make a 10-cent bet?
先生我能不能赌10美分
A whole dime? You're a plunger, sir.
赌完一角，你可真敢冒险先生
Well, I ain't so altogether sure I could hit a moving target without buckshot.
这你看不用大弹头，我不敢肯定能不能射中移动的目标
I used to be fair with a scattergun...
以前猎枪我还玩的可以
...but then that was when the bird wasn't too far away or flying too fast.
但那都是鸟离我不远或飞不太快的情况
Them plates, I just don't see how you manage.
这些盘子我不知道你怎么做到的
Well, I'll be damned.
啊，我真该死
- How are you, GiI? - No great complaints.
―过得怎样，吉尔 ―没什么好抱怨的
How long has it been? Lordy, I'd hate to say.
咱们多久没见了，老天真不想算
Quite some time.
有些日子了
Where you been all these years?
这些年都到哪儿去了
Here and there. Quite a little enterprise you've got.
这里去去，那里去去，你这个公司不错嘛
Well, Steve, it's easier than punching cows...
怎么说呢，史蒂夫，总比赶牛强一点
...and it pays off with free drinks when I walk into a saloon.
去酒吧还能喝上几杯免费的
Would it surprise you that the Oregon Kid is the envy...
你说奇怪不奇怪，俄勒冈小子成了英雄
...of every small-minded ribbon clerk and shirttaiI towhead from here to Pocatello?
从这里到帕卡特罗 每个小心眼的载缝 还有那些小黄发人都买俄勒风小子的帐
Well, why not? All these single-handed exploits.
有什么好惊讶的都是些头脑简单的人
Tell me, GiI, who was the Omaha gang? I don't seem to recollect them fellers.
告诉我，吉尔奥马哈帮都是什么人 记忆中他们不是据夫啊
Flagstaff, Monterey, Hondo, I remember we worked them places.
弗菜斯、达夫蒙特、菜宏都我记得 我们曾在他们的地头干过活的
Dodge City and Wichita. Did you ever run with the Earp boys, GiI?
大治城和赤塔 你真的有和伊尔普的小子们比过吗，吉尔
You gotta allow for exaggeration. That's part of playing the game.
你要容忍一点夸张这是游戏必须的
That's not much of a game. A blind man couldn't miss using buckshot.
说什么游戏用这么大的弹头 老头都不会射歪的
It must be something important to bring you here.
你来肯定是为了重要的事情
Looks like you've been riding a long time but not getting far.
在我看来你绕了很长的路 但离目标还很远
Job.
公事
You mean you're still at it? FederaI marshaI?
你是说你还在做那个联邦护卫
You, a bank guard?
你银行保安
I'm transporting gold from the mining camp up there to the bank down here.
把金块从上面的矿营运到这里的银行
Gold bullion, $250,000 worth, the way the letter put it.
金条用数字表示值250000美元
A quarter of a million.
一百万的四分之一
And I could use some help. Can you recommend anyone?
我需要帮手有好介绍么
- I'll give it some thought. - You do that, will you?
―我想一下 ―认真想想好吗
- And let me know. - I will, Steve. I surely will.
―然后告诉我结果 ―会的，史蒂夫，肯定
What do you figure we're gonna do?
你觉得我们该怎么做
Drink champagne, kid, and only the best.
喝香槟去 孩子，这是最好的
- I'd like to see Mr. Samson, please. - He's busy.
麻烦你，我想见萨好森先生 ―他很忙
Would you tell him it's Mr. Judd. Stephen Judd.
麻烦你，告诉他，居德先生找 史蒂夫居德
Just one minute.
稍等
Excuse me, sir.
打扰一下先生
Mr. Judd.
居德先生找您
Have him come in, Abner.
让他进来，艾纳
Mr. Samson will see you.
萨森先生说要见你
Thank you.
谢谢
I'm Luther Samson, and this is my son, Abner.
我是鲁德萨森，这是我儿子艾纳
- He's the vice president. - I'm pleased to meet you, Mr. Judd.
―他是副总裁 ――很高兴见到你，居德先生
Well, I must say, Mr. Judd, I expected a much younger man.
说实话，居德先生，我们希望是个年轻一点的人
- Well, I used to be. We all used to be. - Yes. Yes, of course.
―我年轻过我们都一样 ―对对，这个当然
Mr. Judd, we're more than familiar with your reputation.
居德先生，比起本人我们更熟悉的是你的声誉
But that was made many years ago, and we're dealing in the present, not the past.
但那都是很久以前的名声了 我们不说过去只讲现在
What's the problem?
有什么问题吗
There's only one traiI. One in, one out.
只有一条通路从哪进就从哪儿出
Six miners have been killed trying to get their gold to us.
为了把金块运给我们已经死了六个矿工
Six miners killed and robbed, Mr. Judd.
六个矿工被杀被抢啊，居德先生
SeveraI weeks ago we petitioned for a marshaI, but nothing happened.
几周前我们申请派一个联邦护卫但一点回音也没有
The only law there is too drunk to hit the ground with his hat.
那里唯一的法律就是没法律
The man we send must be completely reliable, to say nothing of being honest.
我们派出的人一定要完全可靠 诚实就更不用说了
We're speaking of gold, Mr. Judd. Twenty thousand dollars worth.
我们说的是金子。居德先生，两万美金的金子
Twenty thousand?
两万
Why, I thought your letter said 250,000.
怎么回事？信里说的好像是25万吧
Our originaI estimate was overly enthusiastic.
我们一开始估计得太乐观了
The strike isn't a mother lode, but it's productive. Slow and steady.
那个山头不是母矿但产量还不错很稳定
- And we intend to get our share. - The days of the forty-niners are past...
―我们要我们应得的那份淘金汉的时代已经过去了
...and the days of the steady businessmen have arrived.
现在是属子稳重商人的时代
My usuaI fee is $20 a day. I'll have to charge you 40.
一般我收20美金一天，这次我要收40
- Forty dollars a day? - For what?
―40一天！干什么要这么贵
For two extra men. I don't intend to go four days without sleeping.
多雇两个人的费用 我可不打算没日没夜地干四天
- The question is- - Can I do it?
―问题是我能不能胜任
I can't answer that by talking, only by doing it.
我不吹牛用行动说话
If you two wanna talk about it, you go ahead, and I'll read the contract.
两位要商量的话尽管商量 我要看看合同
Well, I guess that'll be all right.
这样好吧
- In private, if you please. - Well...
不介意的话，我想单独看
...you can go in there.
你可以到那里面去
Well, the contract's all right. How about me? Any doubts?
好了合同没什么问题 关于我还有什么疑问
If not, I'll sign it.
没有我就签了
Well, I guess it's all right.
好，我想没什么问题了
That old man is Steve Judd? He don't look like much to me.
那老家伙就是史蒂夫居德 我看没什么大不了的
Son, I wore a star for six years with that old man.
小子 我跟了他六年
I was his deputy most of the time. Once he was mine.
大部分时间我都是打副手 只有一次他做了副手
I just don't figure him to be any trouble, that's all.
我只是不觉得他会挡我们的路 没别的意思
I hope you're right, boy. I surely hope you're right.
希望你是对的孩子真希望你是对的
I'll be at the lion. You demonstrate how impressed you are, with your mouth shut.
我来和他谈 你把真本事拿出来就行了 别说话
- Hi, Mr. Westrum. - Evening, honey.
―你好 维斯特恩先生 ―晚上好 宝贝
Hello, Heck.
你好 赫克
- Stop that! - What did I do?
住手 我做什么了
Never mind what you did. Don't do it in here.
我不管你做了什么 别在这里做
- Can I pick you up in an hour? - I think so.
―一小时后来接你怎样 ―没问题
Too bad, because Heck won't be there.
可惜了 赫支不能去了
- Still keeping records, eh? - You know me. Creature of habit.
―又在记录啊 你知道的老习惯了
Somebody else wants to know you. My partner, Heck Longtree.
这是我要介绍给你认识的我的搭档赫支朗斯特伊
You'd blush to hear the way he admires you.
你要听了他有多崇拜你都要脸红
- How do you do? - Howdy.
你好―好
Have a chair.
坐吧
Showing your age, aren't you?
老了不是
Interfering in a young man's love life.
开始干涉年轻人的爱情了
He's got more important things on his mind. Haven't you?
他有更重要的事情是吧
Haven't you? Yes, sir, and so have I.
是吧是这样的先生我也一样
Been considering your problem. Think I can solve half, perhaps the whole thing.
考虑过你的问题我想我可以解决一半甚至整个问题
I know a fellow who's got an overwhelming hankering...
我认识一家伙很想要试试以前那些活儿的
A man would have to be pretty hard up to want to risk his life for $ 10 a day.
这个人肯定手头很紧 要不也不会为了10美金一天干了
Not hard up. Just fed up.
不是缺钱 只是厌了
Outshooting rubes for nickels and dimes. Takes free drinks to put me to sleep.
厌了整天跟那些乡巴老打枪赢个一毛几分的 然后到酒吧和几杯免费酒 睡大觉
My partner feels the same way.
我搭档的感觉和我一样
- I don't think I'd wanna hire a boy. - What do you mean, a boy?
―我不想雇个小男孩 ―男孩 你什么意思 什么男孩
Steve, this boy's a good deaI less than green.
史蒂夫这男孩绝对不是一张白纸
- He can't have much behind him. - That's where you're wrong.
―他肯定没几两水 ―那就你错了
He's been dogging after me for better than three years.
他已经跟了我三年多了
Pretty.
好枪
Too bad he can't keep it clean.
可惜他没有好好爱惜
Boys nowadays. No pride. No self-respect.
现在的男孩没荣耀感没自尊
Plenty of gall, but no sand.
满腹牢骚不做实事
- Now, you take that race today- - What about that race?
―就说今天的比赛好了 ―今天的比赛有什么问题
Well, at that distance, no horse in the world could beat a cameI.
那距离世上根本没有哪匹马能跑过一头骆驼
Are you calling me a cheat?
你说我作弊
Well, if he don't, I will.
他不说就我来说
Go get them, tiger. You're doing fine. Just fine.
给他们点颜色看看 小子 你打的不错 很好
- What do you think, Steve? - I think he's wonderfuI.
―你觉得怎样史蒂夫 ―我觉得他棒极了
What's the matter, partner? Your rheumatism bothering you?
怎么啦 搭档 风湿发作了
I'm used to working with my brain, not my backside.
我习惯了用脑子干活又不是用背
- You think you can talk him into it? - One way or another.
―你觉得你能说服他吗 ―不成功便成仁
I'd just as soon we'd split it two ways instead of three.
别分三份了 干脆就分两份
Kid, you've got an awfuI lot to learn.
你要学的还多着呢 孩子
- Good afternoon.
下午好 下午好
Joshua Knudsen's the name.
我叫约书亚努森
This is GiI Westrum and Heck Longtree.
这两位是吉尔维斯特恩和赫支朗斯特伊
My name is Judd. Stephen Judd.
我是居德 史蒂夫居德
- I've heard the name. - We're on our way to coarsegold.
―我听过这个名字 ―我们要去库尔斯金矿
Could you furnish accommodations for the night?
可以借宿一晚吗
I've got no room in the house, but I won't object if you wanna stay in the barn.
屋里没空房了 但你们愿意谷仓的话 我没意见
Thank you, sir. If you could spare us a few eggs, we'd be glad to pay for them.
谢谢你 先生 能给我们几个鸡蛋吗 我们可以付钱
Well, one you can have. Because the Lord's bounty is not for sale.
可以免费给一个 因为上帝的恩惠是买不到的
- The rest are a dollar each. - A dollar each?
―再要多的一块钱一个 ―一块一个
How do those short-legged chickens lay eggs so high?
就那些短腿母鸡生的蛋能卖这么责
Levity in the young is like unto a dry gourd with the seeds rattling around.
年轻人的浮躁就像是一片干土地到处是腐烂的种子
My daughter, Elsa.
我女儿 娥莎
- How do you do? - Pleased to meet you.
―你好很高兴见到你
- Likewise. - Go start supper.
同感
For the good reason I told you to. Did you hear what I said?
我说换就换 没听见我的话吗
- I think it's a reaI pretty dress. - Thank you.
我觉得裙子很漂亮―谢谢
Put your horses in the corraI yonder.
马可以牵到那边的畜栏去
Supper will be ready in an hour. No charge. The Lord's bounty-
晚饭大约一个小时后上 免费是上帝的恩惠
- Is not for sale. - Thank you, sir.
―上帝的恩惠不卖 ―谢谢你先生
Think of all that going to waste up here.
想想这些放在这真是浪费
Like the fellow said, gold is where you find it.
人家说的金子就在你找到它的地方
And if it's not yours, don't covet it.
还有金子不属于你 别想占有它
Don't worry. The Lord's bounty may not be for sale...
别担心孩子 上帝的恩惠不卖
...but the deviI's is, if you can pay the price.
魔鬼的恩惠可是卖的 只要你出得起钱
There's a lot of truth in those words, Heck.
这些话说的很对 赫支
Yeah?
是吗
- Yeah. - Supper's ready.
―对晚饭好了
Gentlemen.
先生们
Heavenly Father, we thank thee for the food on this table.
神圣的主父感谢您赐给我们食物
...to walk in thy path...
带领他们走您曾经走过的路
...that they may not suffer thy wrath and thy vengeance.
保佑您的愤怒和仇恨不会降临在他们头上
Bless us, O Lord, and these our guests...
主啊保佑我们还有我们的客人
...and forgive them the mercenary desires which brought them here.
原谅他们抵挡不住利益的诱惑来到这里
Amen.
阿门
Thanks for entering a plea on our behalf, but what's this about mercenary desires?
谢谢您为我们祈祷 利益的诱惑是什么意思
You're on your way to coarsegold. Them that traveI there do so for one reason.
你们不是要去库尔斯金矿吗 到那里去的人只有一个目的
To traffic in gold.
金子交易
Which to possess is to live in fear, to desire, to live in sorrow.
财富让生活充满恐惧欲望 给生活带来忧伤
But we're not trafficking, sir. Merely transporting.
可我们不是去交易先生 我们只负责运送
It says in the Book, Gold is a stumbling block to them that sacrifice to it...
圣经说对子运送金子的人金子必定成为他们的绊脚石
...and every fooI shall be taken therewith.
思蠢的人就会上当
A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches.
好名声是上帝的挑选不是来自财富
A loving favor rather than silver and gold.
是上帝的恩惠不是金银能代替的
Proverbs, chapter 22.
箴言章22章
Into the land of trouble and anguish come the old lions...
充满了动乱和痛苦的大地上走着勇敢的人们
...and they shall carry their riches on the shoulders of young asses...
他们让思蠢的年青人背上财富
Isaiah, chapter 30, verse six.
以塞亚书50章第六版
That mining town is a sinkhole of depravity.
这个矿城就是一个堕落的臭水池
A place of shame and sin.
充满了罪和恶
According to Father, every place outside this farm is a place of sin.
在父亲眼里农场以外的世界都是罪和恶的世界
- That'll do. - You don't have to preach at everybody.
―够了 别对每个人说教
You cook a lovely ham hock, Miss Knudsen. Just lovely.
你煮的火腿很好吃 努森小姐 味道很好
Appetite, chapter one.
胃口章第一章
Give me a toweI, and I'll dry.
毛巾给我帮你擦珠子
Thanks just the same. You hadn't better.
不用了 谢谢你 真好
Sometimes I think there's nobody left in the world but my father and me.
有时候我会觉得这世上只剩下我和父亲两个人了
It's a crime. A girI like you being stuck up on this old stump ranch.
做孽啊像你这样的女孩子要困在这老农场里
A girI like you ought to be living in the city.
你这样的女孩就应该到城市里去
San Francisco, say.
比如说旧金山
- You've been there? - Plenty of times.
你去过
I never been anywhere.
我哪儿都没去过
He won't even take me to town when he goes after supplies.
买东西的时候 父亲也不肯带我进城
He says the men would stare at me.
他说那些男人会盯着我看
Suppose on the way back, I was to pick you up...
回来的时候 如果我来接你
...and take you to San Francisco...
带你去旧金山
...or Denver.
或者去丹佛
- Chicago, even. - Elsa, who you talking to in there?
―甚至是芝加哥 ―娥莎 你在那和谁说话
To myself. You'd better go.
跟自己 你得走了
- I'll meet you outside. - I can't.
―我在外面等你 ―不行
I'll wait for you by the corraI.
我会在畜栏旁边等
That boy you trained personally shows a substantiaI lack of judgment.
你训练的那个男孩好像缺乏判断力
Showing your age, aren't you?
你也老了不是
Interfering with a young man's love life?
开始干涉年轻人的爱情了
Well, I'm not paying him $ 10 a day to go mooning after some girI...
给他10块钱一天可不是让他来泡妞的
...whose old man's about to hind-end him with a load of buckshot.
何况人家的父亲正拿着上膛的枪等着他呢
Sara Truesdale.
莎拉特鲁斯蒂丽
There's no resemblance at all.
一点都不像
Oh, maybe not in the features, but the way she smiles.
不是说长相是她笑的样子
There's the same look in her eyes when you talk to her.
她听你说话的眼神一模一样
The kind of look that makes you feeI you've said something reaI important.
好像你说了很重要的事情那时候的眼神
You and Sara always looked so right together.
你和莎拉总是那么合拍
I can't say I blamed her for not marrying you.
我不是怪她没有和你结婚
Forgetting the lousy money we made, what woman wants to sit around...
先别说我们可怜的酬劳 那个女人愿意坐着干等
...waiting for her husband to be brought home with his head shot off?
等回来的却是脑袋开花的丈夫
I wonder if I can get these fixed in Coarsegold.
我在想能不能借库尔斯金矿改变这一切
I guess losing Sara is what you might call a hazard of our profession.
你肯定要说失去莎拉就是我们这一行的风险
That rancher she married... Stacey, is it?
她嫁的那个农场主好像叫斯塔支
He's doing fine up in Idaho. Got a big ranch there.
他在艾德荷混得不错有个大农场
Raises blooded horses.
养这么好的马
- And children too, I hear. - Grandchildren now.
―听说还有了小孩 ―孙子都有了
Three of them.
三个
That right, Steve?
这样好吗史蒂夫
Yep, that's right.
好怎么不好
Three grandchildren. Think she's happy, Steve?
个外孙觉得她幸福吗史蒂夫
If my sleeping bothers you, don't you bother to let me know.
你对我睡觉有什么不满别跟我说
Sorry.
对不起
Evening.
晚上好
- You surely took your time. - I shouldn't be here at all.
你还真是慢悠悠的―我不该来的
Well, why? Does the night air bother you?
为什么你不喜欢夜晚的空气
I love the night air.
我最爱夜晚的空气了
The thing is, I'm what you might call engaged.
问题是可以说我已经有婚约了
- Sure you are. - It's the truth.
你是有了我说真的
His name is Billy Hammond.
他叫比利赫尔曼
He asked me to marry him.
他向我求婚
SeveraI times.
求了好几次
I said I thought I probably would.
我说我可能会嫁他
You'll see him in coarsegold. He's a miner at the strike, doing reaI well.
去到库尔斯金矿 你就能见到他 他是那的矿工 做得很好
Well, if he's in coarsegold...
既然他在库尔斯金矿
...and you're here...
而你在这
...I don't see any harm in talking.
我们谈谈也没有坏处啊
You! Get in the barn and stay there!
你滚进谷仓呆着
And you, go to the house.
你进屋去
The mouth of a strange woman is a deep pit...
陌生女人的嘴是无底的深渊
...and him that is abhorred of the Lord shall fall therein.
憎恨上帝的人才会投身其中
- Won't you never learn any decency? - We were only gonna talk. Talk.
―你就不能学得庄重一点 ―我们只是在聊天聊天
- The likes of him don't stop at talking. - The likes of him.
那种人不可能只是想聊天
Every man I meet becomes "the likes of him. "
我见过的男人都成了“那种人”
- He's no good. I see it in his face. - That's all you see.
――他不是好东西 看他的脸就知道了 ―就你看得到
Billy Hammond came here twice. You said he was eviI.
比利赫尔曼才来了两次 你就说他是魔鬼是罪犯
I'm your father. I've got to keep the dirt away.
我是你父亲 我得把那些不好的赶走
- Protect you from the wrong kind of men. - That's everyone.
―保护你以防你遇到不好的男人 ―你根本不让我见人
Every single man is the wrong kind of man. Except you.
每个男人都不好 除了你
I promised the next time you hit me, you'd be sorry for it.
我发誓下次你再打我 你会后悔的
For my mouth shall speak truth...
我必须说真话
...and wickedness is an abomination to my lips.
邪恶是我的双唇不能容忍的
All the words of my mouth are in righteousness.
我口中的每一句话都是正当的
Receive my instruction and not silver...
接受我的指示不是银子
...and knowledge rather than choice gold.
接受我的教导而非金子
For wisdom is better than rubies.
智慧要比红宝石珍责
In about 30 years, you'll like the feeI of it too.
50年后你也会喜欢这样的
Pick that up. These mountains don't need your trash.
捡起来这些山可不需要你的垃圾
Dandy pair of boots you got here.
这轻 真不赖
Juan Fernandez made those boots for me in San Antone. SpeciaI order.
胡安佛南德圣地亚哥给我做的 轻特制的
I had a hell of a time getting him to put that hole in there.
我费了好大的劲 才硬让他给我弄了这个洞
A fine craftsman, but he never did understand the principle of ventilation.
他是个好工匠可惜不懂得通风的道理
I remember Juan. Always felt the boot should cover the foot.
我记得胡安 他觉得鞋子就得包住脚
Short-sighted.
只看到眼前
Remember Doc Franklin, the fancy boots he wore with the flaps over the toes?
还记得老迪支富兰克林吗 他那双轻 才神奇 轻头大开
- Old Doc. Know what happened to him? - I heard he died.
―老迪支 他后来怎样了知道吗 ―听说他死了
That's right. Old Doc.
是呀 老迪支
Gave 30 years of his life to make the West safe for decent people.
十年都用在保护西部这些体面的人上了
You'd have wept to see the way they turned out to pay tribute. Three of them.
他死了有多少人去看 听了都伤心 就三个
Well, when I'm buried, I won't much care who comes to the funeraI.
要是我死了 我才不在乎多少人来参加葬礼呢
I was commenting on the fairest flower that grows within the human heart:
我只想评论一下人们心中那朵最美丽的鲜花感恩
The only gratitude I expect is my paycheck. Twenty dollars' worth.
我唯一在乎人们对我的感恩 就是我的工资20美金一天
- That satisfies you? - Well, I guess that's all I can hope for.
―这样就满足了 ―我想要的就这些了
Is it?
真的
According to my contract, it is. come on, let's get moving.
合同是这么写的 快点上路吧
- He don't know what you're talking about. - He will, in time.
你在白费口舌
When we're ready, let's bend a gun over his head and take the gold.
等我们弄好了给他一枪 拿着金子走人
You couldn't get close enough to Steve Judd to saddle his horse.
你连他的马鞍都碰不到
Well, you could.
那你可以啊
Yes, I could, but I won't.
是的 我可以 但我不会
Unless I have to.
除非万不得已
I hope heaven forgives us for earning this easy money.
上帝原谅我们这样不费力气就拿到报酬
I seem to remember a man hankering for some old-time activity.
我好像记得某人说过很想再从操旧业的
I'd like to see some old-time mountains.
我只是想来看看以前这些山
As I recall, they sure were a lot easier to get around in.
没记错的话以前他们可是好走多了
You sure complain a lot in your old age.
你怎么老抱怨年龄
Well, I got something to complain about.
我有抱怨的理由啊
You're earning twice the money for taking the same risk.
同样的风险你却能拿两倍的报酬
Plus possessing all the other rewards you've gathered...
再加上其它的奖励
...during your years of loyaI service.
这么多年忠诚的付出
A bluegrass thoroughbred, silver-mounted saddle...
一匹好马镀银马鞍
...magnificent wardrobe. I'm envious.
漂亮的衣柜 我真妒忌
What more could a man expect? What more can a man hope for?
还有什么是你想要的 还想什么呢
You forgot to mention my two-dollar watch.
你忘记算我那个两美元的手表了
Waste of breath.
白费口舌
What else could a man expect?
还能希求什么
I got to thinking about that one time.
我也想过这个问题
I keep records. When I became a lawman, the world lost a first-class bookkeeper.
我一直有记录 我成了护卫 世界从此损失了一个一流的簿记员
So to pass the time one day, I calculated what it was worth getting shot at.
为了打发时间 我算了一下吃子弹的价钱 算出来是100块
You'd have earned quite a sum by now.
那你赚了不少啊
Getting hit, I figure that's worth anywhere from 1000 on up.
如果是被打的价钱一拳大枚比1000块还责
- That's 3000 I know you got coming. - Four brings it up to date.
以后还会升啊―一共四次
And when you tally up all those fights and bushwhackings and cold camps...
我把那些打斗游击战扎营
...six months out of work. You add them all up, and I'd figure...
六个月没工作把这些都加起来
...I was owed about all the gold we could carry out of these mountains.
我算了一下我们从这些山里能搬出来的金子就是我的应得价钱
It sure is.
确实
Heck!
赫克 我可以跟你们一块走哩
- I do. - I'll second that.
我有关系 我也有
My advice is turn the horse around and ride back where you belong.
我建议你调个头回你的地方去
I'm not going back to my father. I'm going to Coarsegold to marry Billy Hammond.
我不要回爸爸那里 我要去库尔斯金矿和比利赫尔曼结婚
Why do you wanna do a foolish thing like that?
你怎么这么蠢
That's my affair.
那是我的事
She's right, Heck. Our business is transporting gold, not girls.
她说对了 赫支 我们的任务是运送金子不是女人
Thanks for paying back our hospitality. Those ham hocks and everything.
真感谢你们这样报答我们的招待
...but not strong enough to bring you under these conditions.
但还不至于在这种情况下把你带上
I'll ride by myself.
我可以自己骑一边
We can make three miles before it gets dark.
天黑前我们还能走5里
Right. Got to cover ground.
对得赶路了
Too bad. This is certain mountain-lion country.
那惨了 这里很多狮子出没
It sure is.
就是
Well, build a good fire. It will scare them off.
这样好了 生起一大堆火可以吓走它们
I couldn't sleep tonight with the thought of Elsa by herself.
想到娥莎独自一人我肯定睡不着
I'll stay with her and meet you in Coarsegold. Go on ahead.
我留下来陪她到时候在库尔斯金矿碰面 你们走吧
Those mountain lions, some don't scare so easy.
山里的狮子有些不是这么容易就能吓倒的
Come along, girI.
来吧 女孩
- Do you remember old man Teaford? - Oh, yeah.
―记得老家伙狄佛吗 ―哦，当然
All night, Logan.
够了 罗根
Way up, Logan.
继续聊罗根
You think so?
真的
Pa had me cut it short.
爸爸让剪短的
It sort of fits the shape of your head, when you see it from the side.
从这边看很称你的头形
Yeah. Like that.
对 就是那样
You know, most girls don't know the first thing about their hair.
知道吗，很多女孩都不知道怎么弄头发
I guess you're an authority on what most girls do.
女孩该做什么，你应该是个权威吧
Well, I've studied the subject.
嗯，我研究这个
Not just what they do, but why.
不只是做什么，还有为什么那么做
Now, you take this getting married.
就拿你要结婚这事说吧
Do you think that's such a good idea?
这样做真的好吗
If I didn't, I wouldn't be here.
要不我就不会出现在这儿了
My guess is, you're doing it to get away from your pa. To get even, maybe.
我猜你只是想避开你父亲 或许是想跟他对着干
I guess your guess is as good as anybody's.
我想你猜得跟任何人都一样
Well, if it's wrong, how come you ran away?
如果不是这个原因 那你为什么跑
Because my father doesn't want me to get married.
因为父亲根本不希望我结婚
If I can find a decent young man.
只要我能找到一位体面的年轻人
But nobody's decent, according to him.
但在他的眼里没有人是体面的
You included.
你也不是
He said you were no good.
他说你一无是处
He said the likes of you don't stop at talking.
他说你这种人不只满足于聊天
You know, he has a point there.
嗯他说的有点道理
Don't move!
别动
Don't move, Elsa.
别动娥莎
No! Heck, no! Let me go! No! No!
不要赫支不要放开我不不
Let me go!
放开我
My, oh, my.
嗯惨了
When I questioned you about him...
我问你关子这小伙那时
...I should've gone more into the subject of character.
我该问多一点关子人格的
I hope that's a mistake I won't live to regret.
希望这个失误不会让我后悔一辈子
Good fight. I enjoyed it.
打得漂亮我喜欢
That old man?
老家伙是吗
That old man is about half rough.
这老家伙还硬着呢
- You learned a lesson, didn't you? - I surely did.
学到教训了吧 学到了
Got room for another?
还有别的吗
Let her fly.
不搞她了
We're not here for romance. Understand me, son?
我们不是来谈情说爱的听明白了吗小子
Yes, sir.
是先生
I hope Mr. Judd didn't hurt you too bad.
希望居德先生没有把你打得很伤
- I guess it's kind of my fault. - What do you mean, "kind of"?
我想我可能也有错―什么意思，’可能，?
I acted silly. I'm sorry.
我反应过度了对不起
I do like you, Heck.
我对你有好感的赫支
Save the sugar talk for your Billy boy. I don't need it.
甜言蜜语留给你那个小比利吧我不需要
What you need's the kind of girI who'd go with you to San Francisco or Denver.
你要的是肯跟你去什么旧金山丹佛的女孩
And there's plenty of them.
这样的女孩排着队在等我呢
I changed my mind. You got just what you deserve!
我改变主义了你活该
You got something to say?
你又想说什么
No, I think she about covered everything.
没有了该讲的都被她讲了
Lovely place. A beauty spot of nature.
真漂亮自然保留的好地方
A Garden of Eden for the sore in heart and short of cash.
治愈伤心和缺钱的伊句园
We didn't come here to enjoy the scenery.
我们不是来观光的
The High Sierra Crochet and Garden Society...
高山织毛衣公司和养花团体好像正在开周会啊
When we get located, pass the word that we're in camp and ready for business.
安定下来之后把消息放出去就说我们扎好营等着收金子了
And you, find out where the Hammond claim is and take her there.
你找到赫尔曼的地盘把她带过去
Why me?
为什么是我
Because Steve and I are gonna be busy collecting gold.
因为史蒂夫和我要忙着收金子
Not too late to change your mind.
现在改变主意还不晚
I came to Coarsegold to be married. And that's what I'm gonna be. Married.
我来库尔斯金矿是为了结婚的这就是我要的结果成婚
- Well, good luck, then. - All the happiness in the world.
―那祝你好运让全世界的快乐来到你身边
Welcome to Coarsegold.
欢迎来到库尔斯金矿
This seems to be the place to find it.
也只有在这里才能看见这个了
You might be in for a big surprise.
你可能会大受打击
How do you know Billy boy still wants to marry you?
你怎么知道人家比利还想跟你结婚
- What do you care? - I don't.
你担心什么
This the Hammond claim?
这是赫尔曼的地盘吗
- Who wants to know? - I do. I'm looking for Billy Hammond.
―谁问的我我找比利赫尔曼
You found him.
你找到了
Billy!
比利
Howdy, Elsa!
你好娥莎
I can't believe it, honey.
真不敢相信宝贝
Looks like the girI he's been going down the mountain to see.
看来是他下山去见的那个女孩
I'll say one thing, she's sure worth the trip.
照我说她来这越位了
Wish I'd got there first.
真希望我是第一个
Looks like a warm one.
看起来是个温柔的女人
- Hey, where's your pa at? - Back home.
铬你父亲呢―在家
You mean you run off and come all the way up here just to see me?
难道你跑出来了一路跑来这里见我
See you?
见你
I brought my mother's wedding dress.
妈妈的结婚礼服我都带来了
- If you still want to. - If I want to?
如果你还愿意―愿意
If he don't, you got four others to choose from.
他不愿意你还有咱四个吸
Sweet thing like you ought to have the pick of the litter.
像你这样的美人儿就是完全可以挑最好的
- No rush about making up your mind. - Don't listen.
别忙着做决定别听他们乱说
We're gonna get married tonight.
我们今晚就结婚
I guess that will be all, Mr. Longtree.
应该没什么事了朗斯特伊先生
By the way...
等等
...just who is Mr. Longtree?
谁是朗斯特伊先生
I rode up with him from the farm.
他陪我从农场骑马过来的
- That's a couple of days on the traiI. - That's right. Two days, two nights.
路上花了几天吧―对两天两农
A couple of nights.
几个晚上
A couple of nights on the traiI.
路上几个晚上
Billy!
比利
There were two other men with us from the bank in town.
一起还有两个银行的人
Besides, Mr. Longtree was a perfect gentleman.
而又朗斯特伊是个真正的绅士
How come? Something wrong with him?
怎么他有毛病
Well, now, I don't think I ever met a perfect gentleman before, Mr. Longtree.
哈我可从来没见过什么真正的绅士朗斯特伊先生
You come back and see us reaI soon now, you hear, Mr. Longtree?
回头给你看看什么是绅士听见了吗朗斯特伊先生
Jimmy, Sylvus, Elder, come on down here. I want you to meet my woman.
吉米苏维尔斯额德下来来见见我的女人
Come on.
来呀
Elsa, honey, this is Jimmy. He's the baby of the family.
娥莎宝贝这是吉米他就像这里的小孩
And that's Sylvus. He's been doing our cooking, as you can see.
那是苏维尔斯很明显他是掌厨的
And the one on the end is Elder. He's the head of the clan.
边上这个是额德他是这儿的头
I want you to meet my favorite brother. Henry! Get down here now! Come on.
还有来见见我最亲爱的兄弟事利快下来现在快点
Henry's sort of our banker, you might say.
可以说事利差不多就是我们的银行家
come on, honey, I'll show you my tent.
过来宝贝给你看看我的帐篷
It looks like you've got a pretty good claim.
看来你这地方很不错啊
It's a gold mine. Why don't you come over and take a look.
这可是金矿宝贝过来看看呀
You're invited too.
你也来
- Find Billy Hammond? - Yeah.
找到比利赫尔曼了
What difference does it make? She wanted him, now she's got him.
有什么关系呢她要他现在她称心了
I don't want a shave.
我不要刮胡子
Well, Jimmy, you're gonna get shaved whether you want to or not.
不管要不要你都得把胡子刮了
You've been running around with that peach fuzz long enough.
你带着那些毛渣乱晃得够久了
We want that girI to know she's marrying into a family of men.
我们要让那女孩明白她嫁进了一个男人的家庭
Hey, Billy.
铬比利
Thank you, Sylvus.
谢谢苏维尔斯
Now hauI it.
把这个拿走
What's that for?
为什么
You're leaving.
你得走了
I see no sense in moving out just because you're honeymooning.
为什么你度蜜月我要离开
I don't have time to explain it to you, brother. Just get out.
我没时间跟你解释老兄出去
I ain't going.
我不出去
You just did.
你已经出来了
Takes care of him.
对他留个心眼
- I gotta clean up in here. - Plenty of time for that later.
我得把这里打扫一下―以后大把时间
- No. I wanna do it now. - No, you don't.
不我要现在扫―不不要
- But the place is filthy. - It'll wait. It'll wait.
“可这里又乱又脏先放一放放一放
Let go, Billy.
放开比利
- Billy, let me go! - All right.
比利放开我―好好好
Calm down.
冷静点
Come on, honey.
来宝贝
See you later.
稍后见
If you need any help...
需要帮忙的话
...fastening up your wedding dress, you just holler, you hear?
比如穿礼服什么的大叫一声就行知道吗
I'll manage.
我自己能行
First drink is best, east or west.
第一杯是最好的哪都一样
- Let him go. Turn him loose. - There we go.
放开他让他起来―完成了
Jimmy, we're gonna make a man of you now.
吉米多亏我们现在你是个男人了
Say, Henry.
我说事利
I've been wanting to ask you something. Something's been on my mind.
我一直想问你个事
Was you planning to bathe for the wedding?
为了我的婚礼你打算洗个澡吗
No, sir.
不先生
You ain't gonna clean up for your brother's wedding?
兄弟的婚礼你也不把自己弄干净点
No, sir, I ain't.
不我不会
I didn't wash when cousin got wed back home.
在家我堂兄结婚时我也没洗澡啊
That bride didn't seem to mind none. Did she, Billy?
新娘一点都介意的对吧比利
Now there'll be none of that.
没那回事
None of what?
没什么
You know something, Sylvus?
知道吗苏维尔斯
Billy is getting small-minded about that woman.
为了那女人比利变小气了
And a might feisty.
脾气很大
A few drinks under his belt, he'll change his mind.
几杯酒下肚就不同了
Now, liquor always did have a softening effect on Billy.
对 嗯 酒总是能让比利软化
I hate to get married with one of my brothers...
对 酒总是能让比利软化
Yeah, that so?
嗯是这样吗
You wouldn't want that sweet thing to think we're less than quality, would you?
你也不想那甜妞觉得我们低俗对吧
The only thing I know is that after tonight...
我只知道过了今晚
Get him in there.
把他弄进去
All right, let him up.
好了让他起来
- Henry. Henry. - Henry.
―事利事利―事利
- Come on now, Henry. - Easy now.
别这样事利―放松
- We're just funning you, Henry. - Come on, Henry.
唤开玩笑罢了事利―别这样事利
- Easy.
―放松―放松事利
Put the knife up now. You're gonna cut yourself.
收起刀子别伤了自已
Is that a smile I see on his face?
他在笑吗
Easy now, Henry.
放松事利
Come on, boys.
来呀 小伙们
Drink to the bride!
为新娘干杯
Let's have a drink.
来喝一杯
Stand up, judge. Here comes the bride.
站起来，判官 新娘来了
Come on. Steady now.
来站稳
Here she is, folks, my bride-to-be. Elsa, this here's Judge Tolliver.
就是她了。朋友们，我即将的新娘娥莎 这位是托里弗判官
Pleased to make your acquaintance, my dear.
很高兴认识你 亲爱的
And that there's Kate. She's your bridesmaid.
那是凯特你的伴娘
Welcome to Kate's Place, honey.
欢迎亲爱的
And these ladies over here are Sam and Rose and Belle and Candy.
这边是萨好、罗丝、贝丽卡、恩蒂
- We're your flower girls, honey. - You're beautifuI, girls. BeautifuI.
我们是你的花童，宝贝 很漂亮 你们都很漂亮
Aren't they beautifuI, Elsa?
是不是，娥莎
Let her roll, Charlie!
音乐，查理
Drinks on the house!
大家喝
You come on over and sit down, honey. You must be tired. Poor baby.
过来坐下吧，宝贝。你肯定累了，可怜的东西
We'll all of us have a little drinkie before the formalities.
仪式开始之前，大家都会喝一点的
Now, you take this. Don't be afraid. It'll do you good.
来喝点这个，别怕对你有好处的
Cheers, Elsa.
干杯，娥莎
Heck.
赫支
Eleven thousand, four hundred and eighty-six.
一万零四百八十六
That's a far cry from a quarter of a million.
离25万还远着哪
Fortunes of war.
财富之战
Hardly worth it.
根本不值
All depends on where you stand.
得看你站的位置了
I guess that's right.
对，没错
To a poor man, 11,000 is just as far away as 250,000.
对于穷人一万一就跟25万一样都那么遥远
- Where are you going? - Out for some fresh air. Any objections?
―你去哪出去透透气有意见
We're gathered here in the high mountains in the presence of this august company...
在天主的见证下我们聚集在这里
...to join this man and this woman in matrimony.
参加这位男士和这位女士的婚扎
Now, I'm not a man of the cloth, and this is not a religious ceremony.
我不怎么管穿衣的 这也不是宗教仪式
It's a civiI marriage.
这是个文明的婚礼
But it's not to be entered into unadvisedly...
这不是鲁莽的决定
...but reverently and soberly.
而是虔诚的严肃的
A good marriage has a kind of simple glory about it.
好的婚姻总有一种简洁的光辉
It's almost impossible to keep.
几乎没有维持下去的可能
You see, people change.
要知道人是会变的
That's important for you to know at the beginning.
一开始根本就无法知道
People change.
因为人是会变的
The glory of a good marriage don't come at the beginning.
好的婚姻不会在一开始就体现出来
It's hard work.
是个艰辛的过程
Billy, do you take this woman to be your lawfuI-wedded wife...
比利，你原意接收这位女士做你的合法妻子
- ... until God, by death, shall separate you? - I do.
直到上帝让死亡把你们分开吗 我愿意
What's your name again?
再说一次你的名字
Elsa Knudsen.
娥莎 努森
Do you, Elsa, promise to take this man to be your lawfuI-wedded husband...
你娥莎是否愿意承诺接受这位男士做你的合法丈夫
...until death does separate you?
直到死神把你们分开
I do.
我愿意
Do you have a ring?
有戒指吗
All right, girls, change your clothes.
好了，女孩们去换衣服吧
Henry! Henry, Henry!
比利比利
No, no. Sylvus, Sylvus. Now that's enough, Sylvus.
不，不。苏维尔斯 苏维尔斯 够了 苏维尔斯
Hey, bartender, pour a little more.
铬小子多来点
come on, I'll buy you a drink.
来我请你喝酒
What a party!
伟大的派对
Come on, Billy. Come on, get over there and get acquainted around.
来比利周围走走熟悉熟悉
Let me in there. Let me in there.
到我了到我了
- Have fun, honey. - Billy!
玩的开心宝贝―比利
Billy!
比利
come on, now. It's my turn, Sylvus.
放开到我了苏维尔斯
- I told you not to do that! - Now, wait.
我说了别这样―等等
You had your turn.
你已经轮过了
It looks like Jimmy's making a man out of himself.
看来吉米真的要成为男人了
- I told you not to do that! - Now, don't be like that, Sylvus.
―我说了别这样别这样苏维尔斯
Oh, come on now.
别这样
Now, Sylvus, we got a nice party. Why don't you behave yourself.
苏维尔斯 这么好的派对 你就不能管管自已
You can't hit my brother!
别打我兄弟
Don't leave me.
别离开我
I wish I'd known more about those brothers.
多了解了解那帮兄弟就好了
It's too late now.
现在已经太迟了
- She's married. - Glad they didn't invite me.
―她结婚了还好他们没有邀请我参加
I always cry at weddings.
我经常在婚礼上哭
The more I am around you, the more I can do without your sense of humor.
和你呆了那么久你不说笑我也能活
Come on, break it up! Boys, get over there!
快点分开小伙们分开
Now I said, break it up, and I mean it. Get over there.
我说了分开不是说笑到那边去
Come on, Sylvus, get over here and behave yourself.
快苏维尔斯过来这边管好你自已
Get over there!
滚去那边
No.
不要
Well, now, get on in there!
来现在给我进去
Easy now, Elsa.
放松娥莎
- Listen, Elsa, you come here! - No, Billy!
听着娥莎过来
No, Billy!
不比利
Now, you straighten out, you hear me?
听话点听见了吗
Where's Billy?
比利在哪
I've got some prying brothers.
我那几个兄弟真爱打听
You stay here.
你留在这
She's mine. She's mine. Let go, Henry.
她是我的我的放开事利
- Elsa! - Henry, turn loose of me!
―娥莎―事利放开我
I'm gonna get you.
我要抓到你
- Come back, Elsa. Come back. - Come back, girI.
回来娥莎回来―回来女孩
Come on, get your bride. Billy, get your bride.
快来追回你的新娘比利把你的新娘追回来
Hold it!
别动
Let her go.
放开她
- Where are you going with my wife? - She'll stay with us.
你们带我妻子去哪她现在和我们一起
- I'm taking her to her father tomorrow. - Like hell she will.
明早我带她回去给她父亲―回去你个头
- You can't take a wife from her husband. - Clear case of breaking and entering.
你不能把妻子从她丈夫身边带走
- Elsa's legally married to Billy. Right? - I now pronounce you man and wife.
娥莎和比利是合法夫妻了对吧
- And don't you forget it. - Go along, Elsa.
―别忘了这点 ―先走娥莎
Heck.
赫支
You're not leaving this camp with her. I'll promise you that.
我保证你不可能带着她离开这个营
Go home, Billy.
回去吧比利
What happened? You all right, Billy?
发生什么事了还好吧比利
Where is she? Where is she? I'll kill him. I'll kill him.
她呢 在哪 我要杀了他 杀了他
- Billy! - Where'd he go with her?
―比利他带她去哪拉
- Come on. - Why'd you let him get away with her?
―来你怎么让他把她带走了
The marriage didn't work. We have to take her to her father.
这次婚姻不行我们得带她回她父亲那里
- We've got our hands full already. - I don't like it any better than you do.
史蒂夫我们的麻烦已经够多了―我没比你开心多少
Too big, huh?
太大了
What are they doing there?
他们在干嘛
We're willing to abide by the court's decision if you are.
你们同意的话我们愿意尊照法庭的判决
We'll abide.
好
Don't be scared.
别害怕
- What's wrong? - Billy Hammond wants Elsa.
―怎么拉比利要娥莎回去
They appointed a miners' court to decide it.
他们委托了矿工法庭来判决
- Miners' court? - That's the law, places like this.
―矿工法庭这就是法律这地方的法律
And there's a lot more of them than there are of us.
他们人多势众
Billy's very sorry. Swears it won't happen again. I believe him.
比利对昨晚的事很抱歉
- I wouldn't believe Billy- - I don't wanna go back.
我才不信那个比利我不要回他那去
You were legally married of your own free will.
你们合法结婚了是你自愿的
Please. You can't let him take me back. You can't.
求求你 不能让他带我回去 不行
But whatever they decide, that will have to be it.
可法庭怎么决定你就得怎么做
That don't have to be it. She's not going with him. She stays with us.
谁说的她你能跟他回去她得和我们一起
She stays here! We're packing gold, not petticoats.
她留在这我们来收金子不是来收裙子的
If she stays, I stay.
她留下 我也留下
Well, let's hope the court lets her go with us.
既然这样就希望法庭判她跟我们走吧
Otherwise, we'll be a little short-handed.
不然我们要缺人手了
All right, gentlemen, we can proceed.
好了 先生们可以开始了
In the first place, I married this gaI here last night, up on the hill in Kate's Place.
首先我昨晚和这个女孩结婚了就在山上得凯特酒店
- You saw Judge- - Where can I find Judge Tolliver?
―看到特里弗判官了吗 ―特里弗判官在哪
- At the end of the hall, mister. - He married us legaI and proper.
―大厅尽头先生他为我们单行了合法适当的婚礼
Easy. Sit up.
放松坐起来
A little more.
再起来一点
Thank you, sir.
谢谢你先生
What can I do for you?
能为你做什么
Clear up a little technicality, if you will.
如果你愿意请你澄清一点技术性的事情
About that marriage last night.
关子昨晚的婚礼
They're holding a miners' court. They'll wanna know if it was legaI.
他们告上了矿工法庭想知道是不是合法婚姻
- Of course it was legaI. - Well, I believe that.
当然是合法的―我也信
But the court may want proof, in the form of a license.
但法庭需要证据证书那样的
You got one?
你有吗
Signed by the governor of California.
加利福尼亚州长签字的
Yes, sir, there's no question at all about the legality of this document.
是的 先生 这个文件合法性勿庸置疑
Now, when you testify before that miners' court...
好 你上庭作证的时候
...I'm gonna ask you one question:
我要问你一个问题
"Do you possess a license to marry people in california?"
“你在加利福尼亚有没有主持婚礼的资格”
And you're gonna answer, "No. " Am I clear?
你要回答：“没有” 明白吗
- That's a lie. - No, it isn't. You don't possess it. I do.
―那是撒谎不不是你没资格我才有
You're gonna do as you're told. Understand?
乖乖按我说的做明白了吗
Now, do you recall the question I'm gonna ask?
现在还记得我的问题吗
And what do you answer?
你的回答
No.
没有
Very good.
很好
Let's go.
走吧
According to the law, she's still married to Billy Hammond.
根据法律他还是比利赫尔曼的妻子
You and the law. She can get it nullified.
有你和法律 她就可以让那场婚姻失效
Will that satisfy your ironbound code of ethics?
你那钢铁般的道德感满足了吗
My code satisfies pretty easy, partner.
我很容易满足的搭档
Would it surprise you to know that I was once a lawbreaker?
如果说我原来常做违法的事 你会怎样
Well, bless my stars.
哦，上帝保估
About the age of that boy back there. Skinny as a snake and just about as mean.
我想那男孩这么大的时候狡猾得跟蛇一样又吝啬
Ran with the Hole-in-the-Wall bunch.
整天就和那么一群人混
Gun-happy, looking for trouble or a pretty ankle.
玩枪 要不就找妞
Had the world by the taiI, so to speak.
世界都在掌握之中可以这么说
Then one night, PauI Staniford picked me up.
一天晚上保罗斯坦弗把我抓了起来
He was sheriff of Madera County then.
那时候他是马德拉镇的治安长官
There'd been a fight, and I was drunk. Sicker than a fat dog.
我们打架，我还喝得烂醉如泥
He dried me out in jaiI, and then we went out back...
在监狱里他狠狠地教训了我 出来后我们还是老样子
...and he proceeded to kick the bitter hell right out of me.
他继续对付我，把我翻了个遍
That took some doing.
真不容易
Not much. You see, he was right, I was wrong.
也没有，你看他是对的，我是错的
That makes the difference.
根本没法比
Who says so?
谁说的
Anyhow, when I was able to walk again, I realized I'd learned a lesson from him.
总之我又能站起来走路的时候 我知道我学会了一件事
The value of self-respect.
自尊自重的价值
What's that worth on the open market?
这个在市场上值多少
Nothing to some people, but a great deaI to me.
对一些人来说不值分文 但对我非常重要
But I lost it.
我却把它丢了
These last years, the only work I was able to get was places like Kate's.
这几年我只能在凯特酒店那样的地方工作
Bartender, stick man, bouncer, what have you.
酒信啦 接待啦 保操啦 有什么办法
Not much to brag on.
没什么好夸耀的
- Good to be working again, GiI. - Yeah.
―重新工作 真好啊 吉尔 ―对
You know what's on the back of a poor man when he dies?
知道可怜的老迪支死的时候背上是什么吗
The clothes of pride.
尊严的外衣
And they're not a bit warmer to him dead than they were when he was alive.
和他生前一样这些衣服在他死后也无法给他带来温暖
Is that all you want, Steve?
你要的只有这些，史蒂夫
AII I want is to enter my house justified.
我要的是进家门时问心无愧
Will you stay in town when we get back?
回去之后你们会留在镇上吗
I'm not just certain. Why?
还不确定怎么了
You're right, kid. I've been wasting my breath. Tonight we move.
你说对了，孩子。我只是白费口舌 今晚我们就行动
- I don't know. - You don't know what?
―我不知道 ―什么，你不知道
I started out thinking he was an old mossback...
一开始我觉得他是个老古董
...but I changed my mind. Kind of hate to turn against him.
但后来我改观了现在我不太想和他反目
Are you with me or not?
你是站他那边还是我这边
- What will happen to Elsa? - He'll deliver her.
―那娥莎怎么办 ―他会送她回去的
The thing for you to remember is that we made a deaI.
别忘了，我们可是有约定的
Yes, sir.
是，先生
It all pointed this way.
所有迹象暗示着这样的结果
All that talk about old Doc Franklin, ungratefuI citizens.
所有那些关于老迪支的话 不懂感恩的人们
- What we had coming but never got paid. - It's the truth, isn't it, Steve?
―没有回报的付出 ―都是事实，不是吗？史蒂夫
I knew in my bones what you were aiming for, but I wouldn't believe it.
你的目的我清楚的很 可我就是不愿意相信
I kept telling myself you were a good man.
我坚持告诉自己，你是个好人
- You were my friend. - This is bank money, not yours.
―你是我的朋友啊 ―这是银行的钱又不是你的
And what they don't know won't hurt them.
不知情的人不会受到伤害
Not them. Only me!
你伤的不是他们，是我
Take off your gun belt and toss it over here.
解开枪带扔到这边来
What are you gonna do?
你要怎么做
You always fancied yourself faster than me.
你一直都自以为比我快
Go ahead, draw.
来啊，开枪
Draw, you damned tinhorn!
开枪，你这没用的
That was your second mistake...
那是你第二次犯错
...and the last chance you'll ever get from me.
你再也没有机会了
I'm gonna put you behind bars, GiI.
我要把你投入大牢，吉尔
You'll play hell getting it done.
做吧 你这混蛋
Move!
走
My, oh, my, will you look who's here.
哦 我的妈 看谁来了
Howdy. You made pure fools out of us, stealing that license from Tolliver.
你竟敢耍我们 从塔里弗那偷走了证书
The judge says there's another one on file in Sacramento.
判官说了萨支拉曼多那里还有一份存档的
That means she's still my wife. come on, honey, let's go home.
所以她还是我的妻子 过来宝贝 咱们回家去
She stays with us.
她和我们一起
Looks to me like you been having some trouble.
我看你们有麻烦了
Looks to me like somebody got their finger caught in the cookie jar.
某人的手好像被拷住了呀
You're short-handed, old-timer, but she's all we want.
你人手不够老家伙 可我们要得只是她
All we want, provided we get her now.
只要你现在把她交给我们 别的我们不要
- You heard me. - We'll get her, sooner or later.
―要说的我已经说了 ―我们会把她要回来的迟早
Like hell you will!
去你妈的
You better cut yourself a switch, Mr. Longtree.
你最好准备条棍子 朗斯特伊先生
I don't think you could handle me barehanded.
我可不觉得你能赤手空拳对付我
You all are gonna get yourself a chance to try, directly.
你们都有机会很快了
Come on.
我们走
I have your word you'll return your gun when this is over?
能保证这个完了之后把枪还给我吗
Yes, sir, I reckon you do.
是先生我保证
- I'll go along. - You bet you'll go along.
―我也一起去 ―去你的头
- We're moving into the rocks. - Steve!
―我们到岩石中间去 ―史蒂夫
Shut up! Move!
闭嘴 快走
Move out!
快走
You're really showing your age.
你真的老了
Back in the old days, you'd have checked those rifles before we left camp.
以前出营地之前 你肯定会检查那些来复枪的
I'll get around behind them.
我从后面包围他们
Don't waste your time. They're too far away.
别浪费力气 太远了
He's going around behind us. Cut me loose and give me a gun.
他要绕到我们后面来了 松开我 再给我把枪
I'll get a rifle for you.
我去给你拿把来复枪
Start shooting.
开枪
Sylvus!
苏维尔斯
- He was carrying a rifle. - Let's get out of here!
―他手上有把来复枪 ―我们走
- Looks like they got Sylvus. - I know that. come on! We're getting out.
―看来他们已经拿下苏维尔斯了 ―我知道快点我们离开这里
You got two brothers dead, you talk about running?
两个兄弟倒了 你敢说离开
Come on!
快过来
I wonder where those other three went.
不知道那三个人去哪儿了
- I hope they're not still following us. - Calm your fears, honey.
―希望他们不要再跟着我们就好了 ―别担心 宝贝
My guess is, they gave up and went back to Coarsegold.
照我说 他们肯定放弃了回库尔斯金矿去了
Assuming that's so, I'll have your gun back.
这事算完了我要收回枪了
Do you hear me, boy?
听到我说什么了吗 小子
I'm sorry, Mr. Judd. I guess I was showing off.
对不起 居德先生 我只是卖弄卖弄
- What happens when we get to town? - It's up to the sheriff.
―回到镇上之后我们会怎样 ―那要问治安官了
He's turning us in. You know that. So do I.
他要把我们交出去 你很清楚 我也一样
- Ever hear of Folsom Prison, Heck? - No.
―听说过福尔松监狱吗赫支 ―没有
Well, it's solid rock.
全是坚硬的岩石
During the years we spend there we'll discuss...
呆在那里的接下来几年 我们要讨论一下
...the events of the past few minutes at great length.
刚才那几分钟发生的事情详细地谈谈
And by the time you get out, you won't like him any better than I do now...
等你出来 你就会像我现在这样厌恶他
...which isn't one hell of a lot. Where do I sleep?
这 厌恶 他妈的 一点也不深 我睡哪
Up there. I don't wanna see you till breakfast.
上那边去吃早饭前，别让我看到你
Cut me loose, Steve.
给我松绑，史蒂夫
Why?
为什么
Because I don't sleep so good anymore.
我不像过去那么好睡了
- Good night.
晚晚
My father says there's only right and wrong...
我父亲说世上只有对和错
...good and eviI.
善和恶
Nothing in between.
中间什么也没有
- It isn't that simple, is it? - No, it isn't. It should be, but it isn't.
―其实没那么简单，对吧 ―对，应该这么简单的，但现实不是
What's gonna happen to him?
他会怎么样
The boy? I'll testify for him. They shouldn't be too hard.
那小子，我会为他作证，不会判很重的
Will you testify for Mr. Westrum?
你会为维斯特恩先生作证吗
- No, I won't. - Why?
―不，不会 ―为什么
Because he was my friend.
因为他是我朋友
No place to go.
我们又没地方逃
He's got the horses, and he's got the guns.
马在他那 枪在他那
And it wouldn't take long for Steve Judd to find us.
史蒂夫要找到我们根本用不了多久
Wait a minute, kid. I just had a thought.
等等孩子我想到一个主意
Well, keep it to yourself. I'm fed up with you and your ideas.
自己留着吧你还有你那些主意我受够了
That's all right.
好啊
- Morning.
早上好 早上好
- Where's GiI? - Gone.
―吉尔呢 ―跑了
Why didn't you go with him?
你为什么不和他一起跑
Because I didn't see any future in our partnership.
因为和他搭档，我看不到未来
Come on.
过来
Get up there!
上那去
You wait here.
你们在这边等着
I'll go down and take a look around.
我下去看看情况
Neither does he.
他肯定也不觉得是冒险
I never figured it would turn out this way.
想不到事情会变成这样
chances are I'll be locked up for a while. I've got no call to bring it up.
我很可能会被关上一段时间 我没什么资格这么说
- But maybe when I get out- - I'll be there.
―但或许我出来的时候 ―我等你
What are you doing?
干什么
- That's strange. - What?
―不正常 ―什么
He goes to her grave every day but always in the morning.
他每天都会到她的地里去都是早上
Never in the afternoon.
但从来不会在下午
We're going to the ditch.
我们到沟里去
Now!
现在
I walked right into it.
就差一点
I'm gonna try for the corraI.
我得试试到畜栏那边去
I got him.
射中他了
Well, where's the rifle?
来复枪在哪
On the horse.
马背上
Bad?
很严重
Not yet.
还不算
Partner, what do you think?
搭档你说怎么办
Let's meet them head-on, halfway, just like always.
面对面直接碰面就像以前那样
My sentiments exactly.
跟我想的一样
- You, Hammonds! - What do you want, old man?
―你们姓赫尔曼的 ―想怎样老家伙
He wants a shoveI and six feet of dirt.
他要一把铲和六英寸的土坑
You redneck peckerwoods.
你们这些白痴
You're too chicken-gutted to finish this thing out in the open.
胆小鬼没胆量出来堂堂正正和我们打一场
Two old men against all three of you boys.
两个老人对三个壮小伙
And if them odds ain't enough for you damned dry-gulching Southern trash...
如果这还不能让你们这些该死的 没用的南方垃圾满意
- ... we'll send out the girI. - We're coming!
―我们就把女孩派出去 ―我们出来了
- You hear me, Henry? - Yeah, I hear you.
―听见了吗事利 ―我听见了
You don't have to ask me twice!
同样的话别说两次
- We'll catch them when they raise up. - Ain't you got no sense of family honor?
―他们一起来,我们就打 ―你难道就没有一点家族尊严吗
Start the ball, old man.
开枪啊 老家伙
How'd we figure?
怎么算
- A thousand dollars a shot? - Yeah.
―1000美金一枪 ―好
Those boys sure made me a lot of money.
那些小毛孩真是让我发大财了
They put them all in one spot.
都一块放在坑里吧
I don't want them to see this.
别让他们看到我这个样子
I'll go it alone.
我要自己走
Don't worry about anything.
什么都不用担心
I'll take care of it, just like you would have.
我会处理的就像你做的那样
Hell, I know that.
妈的我就知道
I always did.
我就知道
You just forgot it for a while, that's all.
你只是暂时迷失了而已
So long, partner.
再见了，搭档
I'll see you later.
我很快就去找你